in this video we're gonna talk about
Kepler's third law and the gist of his
third law is that the ratio of the
squares of the periods of any two
planets revolving around the Sun is
equal to the ratio of the cubes of their
mean distances from the Sun so the ratio
of the periods t1 over t2 and that is
the square of those periods it's
equivalent to the cube of their main
distances so that's r1 over r2 raised to
the third power so this equation is
associated with Kepler's third law now
let's talk about how to derive in that
equation so let's say this is the Sun
and here's the earth the Earth orbits
the Sun so therefore the gravity
provides the centripetal force so we're
going to set the gravitational force
equal to the centripetal force so the
gravitational force is the gravitational
constant G times the mass of the Sun
times the mass of the Earth divided by
the square distance between their
centers there's a triple force acting on
the earth is going to be the mass of the
Earth times the V squared over R so we
could cancel em you know we can cancel
one R on both sides so we have G M over
R is equal to V squared now the earth is
moving with constant speed around the
Sun so we can use the equation D is
equal to V T V is the distance divided
by the time and the earth is traveling
in a nearly circular orbit so the
distance around a circle is 2 pi R the
time it takes the revolver on that
circle is a period so therefore we can
replace V squared
with two PI R over T squared tsunami and
makes some more space
so we'll now have his gene times the
mass of the Sun over R is equal to if we
square both sides or net both sides but
just assign two squared is four and then
we're gonna have PI squared times R
squared over T squared
now let's cross multiply so on the Left
we're gonna have G times M s times T
squared is equal to 4pi squared times R
cube now save this portion of the
equation in this form we're gonna use it
later in this video so just make a note
of it
now I'm gonna solve for T squared so I
need to divide both sides by G M so T
squared is 4 pi squared R cubed over G
times M now what I'm going to do is
divide t2 squared by t1 squared so t2 is
going to be 4 pi squared R 2 raised to
the third over GM s based on in this
equation t1 squared is going to be 4 PI
squared R 1 cube over GM s so G and the
mass of the Sun is going to be the same
so we can cancel it and 4pi squared is
going to be the same so we're left with
t 2 squared over t1 squared and that's
equal to R 2 cube over R 1 cubed which
if we want to we can write it as T 2
over T 1 raised to the second power
equals R 2 over R 1 and raised to the
third power so that's how you can derive
the equation that's associated with
Kepler's third law
now let's work on a few practice
problems the mean distance between the
earth and the Sun is 1.5 times 10 to the
11 meters the mean distance between the
Sun and Mars is two point two eight
seven times 10 to 11 meters what is the
period of Mars around the Sun in Earth
days so let's say this is the Sun here's
the earth and here's Mars
so let's say this is the orbit for Earth
and this is the orbit for Mars
now it takes Earth 365 days to orbit the
Sun and it takes Mars some unknown
number of days to orbit it so let's say
if this is t1 we need to find t2 that's
the time it takes from Mars to orbit the
Sun now we have the mean distance
between the Sun of the earth and the Sun
of the Sun that's about 1.5 times 10 to
11 meters so if T 1 corresponds to earth
r1 has to be the distance between the
Sun and the earth now the distance
between the Sun and Mars that's given to
us that's two point two eight seven
times ten to eleven so we're going to
define that as r2 our goal is of
calculate t2
so t2 over t1 squared is equal to r2
over r1 q or if you want to you can
write it this way it might be easier to
do it like this t2 squared over t1
squared is equal to r1 cube with r2 cube
on top so let's say that t1 corresponds
to the earth so it's 365 days squared
and we're looking for T 2 R 1 is 1.5
times 10 to 11 and let's raise that to
the third power
r2 is two point two eight seven times 10
to 11 to the third power so let's cross
multiply first so on the left I'm gonna
have 365 squared times two point two
eight seven times 10 to 11 raised to the
third power and on the right is going to
be one point five times ten to 11 raised
to the third power times t2 squared now
I'm going to divide both sides by this
number so I'm no longer going to have it
on the right side but it's going to be
on the bottom of the left side
so now let's type this in to calculate
t2 squared
so 472,000 180 3.1 that's equal to t2
squared so now when you take the square
root of both sides so t2 is about six
hundred and eighty seven days so that's
how long it takes Mars to orbit the Sun
so one year on Mars is 687 days that's a
long time
one here on the earth is 365 days a year
is to find that as the time it takes for
a planet to orbit the Sun now let's move
on to the next problem
it takes Venus 225 days to orbit the Sun
if the Earth's Sun distance is 1.5 times
10 to 11 meters what is the mean
distance between Venus and the Sun so if
you want to draw a picture let's say
this is the Sun and here is the earth
and let's say here's Venus so this is
the orbit for Venus and this is the
orbit for the earth so it takes Venus
225 days because it's closer to the Sun
for the earth is 365 days we know the
distance between the Sun and the earth
it's 1.5 times 10 to the 11th we need to
find the distance between Venus and the
Sun so let's call it R 2 that's the
missing variable that we're looking for
so using the same equation T 2 over T 1
squared is equal to R 2 over R 1 cube so
T 1 we're gonna apply it for Earth
that's going to be 365 days and T 2
that's going to correspond for the
period for Venus which is 225 Earth days
R 1 is 1 point 5 times 10 to 11 raised
to the third power
so we're looking for arts you in this
problem so just like before we're gonna
cross multiply so it's going to be 365
squared times R 2 cube and that's equal
to 225 squared times 1.5 times ten to 11
raised to the third power so I'm going
to divide both sides by 365 squared so R
2 raised to the third power it's going
to be one point five times ten to eleven
raised to the third power times 225
squared divided by 365 squared so you
should get one point two eight two times
ten to the thirty three now to get hard
raise both sides to the one-third power
so our two is the cube root of that
number which is one point zero eight six
times ten to the 11 meters so as you can
see it's less than the earth-sun
distance because Venus is closer to the
Sun and so it's gonna have a smaller
period number three calculate the mass
of the Sun using the Earth's Sun mean
distance of 1.5 times 10 to 11 now
earlier in his video I mentioned to
highlight this equation which we derived
already G times M s t squared is equal
to 4pi squared R cube so we derive this
equation where the Sun was at the center
and the Earth was orbiting the Sun we
sent this a triple force equal to the
gravitational force and we also replace
the velocity with 2 pi R over T
we were able to get this equation now
all we got to do from that point is
solve for M that's gonna give us the
mass of the Sun so to do that we need to
divide both sides by G T squared
so the mass of the Sun can be calculated
using this equation
it's 4pi squared times R raised to the
third power divided by GT squared so if
you need to find the mass of any planet
or the mass of the Sun you can use this
formula where T is the time it takes for
an object to orbit the Sun or that
planet so let's say if you want to find
the mass of the earth you want to use
the period of the moon because you need
a satellite that's orbiting it if you
want to find the mass of the Sun the
earth is acting like the satellite
because the earth is orbiting the Sun so
you would have to use the period of the
earth but if you want to find a mass of
the earth use the period of the moon for
T so let's go ahead and plug everything
we have so R is the distance between the
Earth and the Sun that's one point five
times ten to 11 raised to the third
power and G is six point six seven times
ten to minus 11 and T is the period in
seconds now it takes about one year for
the earth to travel around the Sun so
that's about 365 days now if you want to
incorporate the leap here and say 365.25
days that's fine too but the answer is
not going to change much it's gonna be
about the same each day contains 24
hours and each hour is 60 minutes and
one minute is equivalent to 60 seconds
so we can cancel the unit days hours and
minutes
so it's 365 times 24 times 60 times 60
so it takes the earth 31 million 536,000
seconds to orbit the Sun and don't
forget to square that number
so you should get two point zero one
times ten to the 30 kilograms so that's
the mass of the Sun so let's say if you
want to calculate the mass of the earth
using that same formula
now in order to calculate the mass of
the earth the earth has to be the object
in the center so we need something
that's orbit in the earth in this case
we're going to use the moon so we need
two things the earth-moon distance which
you can look it up that's about three
point eight four times ten to the eighth
meters and you need the period of the
moon it takes the moon about twenty
seven point four days to orbit the Earth
now we need to convert that value to
seconds so T is twenty seven point four
days and one day is equivalent to 24
hours one hour sixty minutes and each
minute is equivalent to sixty seconds so
it's 27 point four times 24 times 60
times 60 so the period is two million
three hundred sixty seven thousand and
three hundred sixty seconds so that's
how long it takes the moon to orbit the
Earth so now we can plug in everything
so it's four pi squared times three
point eight four times ten to the 8th
meters raised to the third power divided
by the gravitational constant multiplied
by two three six seven three six zero
squared so go ahead and type this in
so you should get about 5.98 times 10 to
the 24 kilograms which is the mass of
the earth